Once there was a village called Goddess Temple
假如我们村叫娘娘庙
high up in the mountains,
在很大很大的山里
Once there was a fever that the world called AIDS.
不知从哪天起 被村人叫做热病的艾滋病
ft snuck into our village softly,
从外面世界悄无声息地来了
and everyone who got it died like falling leaves.
有了这热病
Look, that's me right there.
假如这就是我
My name was Xin,
姓名赵小列
and {was 12,
现在十二岁
Look, there's my dad.
看 这是我驳
Who did
谁干的
ft was weird, seeing myself like that.
真奇怪 假如我这样看着我自己
They said it was dad's fault people got sick,
人家说村里的热病都是我侈害下的
and that Uncle had it coming.
活该我权也有了热病
if fm going to tell our story,t guess it starts from here.
假如 我要给你们讲的故事就从这儿开始
Start?
开始
Do you want me to start?
开始不开始叮
There's a new cure...
有新药了
So forgive the singer if his song is poor—
今天我一定要唱
he wishes you joy and health, longevity!
祝愿大家身体健康 万寿无疆
{hitched a ride upon a cloud
一驾云头三干里
Saw things no mortal sees
三驾云头够九干
leaped from cloud to cloud
云头展够好几展
At immortal speed
也够响几人走几年
The clouds,they parted
这才拨开云头来看
The world appeared before my eyes
两眼不住地四下观
To the east,the boundless sea
往东看到东洋海
To the south,the sacred peaks
往南看到洛迦山
To the west,the temples fair
往西看到雷音寺
To the north,the fragrant springs
往北看到人饮马泉
And the heavens above...
往上看到凌霄宝殿
Yes
有
said no
我说就没有
! said yes
有有就是有.…
What?
咋着
Go ahead, ask Old Zhu.
你把他叫出来 叫出来问问啊 你问啊
He has
有.…就是有
Ask me what?
甚事
There's a cure for the fever, right?
人老柱柱说的
fm not lying!
我没有骗人
You told me yourself,
这老柱柱说的
Sure.
肯定有
There is!
就有
No there isn't!
根本就没有
Oiquan told me
齐全说的
He's standing right there.
他就在那儿了
Dad
区
why bother lying?
你骗人做其
They!ll find out, eventually
你最后能给热病造出个新药啊
Knee! down and apologize
你给全村人奢头
{t's the least you can do
你不奢头也得赔个不是
If there's no cure, fet them hear it from you!
你说没有新药就没新药了
Down on your knees!
你给奢头
Do it!
你给奢头
Grandpa...
外公 卫卫
My son, the blood merchant...
我让你卖人的血
Got blood? Qiquan's your man,
卖血找齐全 随时随地
Anytime, anyplace, at a price that's fair!
方便大家 价格更公道
Grandpa ... we go home
爷爷.我们回家吧
Don't you start, too!
不叫来 你非来
We're going home!
回家 走
Please forgive me...
我对不起咱们全村人
for having a son like that.
生了这么个儿子
I raised him,
我养了他
but I couldn't teach him.
我教不了他
Please remember...
求大家看在
my younger son has the fever, too,
我儿得意也有热病
And my grandson was only 12...
我孙子才十二岁
Even if it was Qiquan's fault you got infected,
就算全村的热病都是齐全采血给染上的
! beg you not to hold it against our family.
也求大家别再往心上记了
Since all the teachers ran off,
自打去年老师吓跑了
and the kids go to school in town,
学生也去了乡里读书
the school is empty.
学校空着
If you're afraid of infecting your families,
要是怕给家里人也传染上
come five in the school,
就到学校来住
and Ni ook after you.
我来照顾
f admit tt
还有
! fied about the medicine.
上头确确实实没说过有新药
They say the fever's a new plague,
人家说热病是绝症是瘟疫
and nothing in the world
全世界
can cure it,
都还没法治
Gee!! Another victim!
热病病死人了 快走
Run run runil!
赶快走吧
And that was the last concert
二强分分唱了一辈子
the old musician ever gave.
不想再唱了
That's our village school
这是我们村的老学校
where grandpa was a caretaker.
我爷爷一直看守着
When the weather got cold,
天最冷的时候
the sick villagers started moving in.
爷爷陆陆续续迎来了村里得热病的人
After ! die,
三朝两日我死了
! want you to take our son
你就达着小军嫁人
and get remarried.
嫁得远远的
Leave this god-awful place,
离开这个鬼地方
Dont worry, ff be fine.
驳在这儿 我吃不了亏
Go on home,
你回吧
But don't forget to visit every day!
每天都来看看我
Here in the school,
都住学校了
aff meals will be communal.
就集体开伙吧
Who volunteers to cook?
谁来做饭呢
{fF you men are too macho for the kitchen,
做饭能难死个英友好汉
fi do it.
我来做
But no disrespect.
只要你们不嫌弃
We'd respect you more in the bedroom!
给大伙有睡都不嫌弃
Now, now, in this school,
都是学校的人
everyone gets treated with respect.
都是学校的人 谁也不嫌弃谁
Same goes for schoo! property,
房屋田舍都是大家的
desks and such,
还有桌子椅子
Treat then with the same respect
娃娃们回学校以后还得要用
you'd show your own wife.
要像自家媳妇一样爱惜啊
Or better yet, someone else's wife!
别人家的媳妇更要爱异
We'll poo! our food stores,
带来的粮食都放到一块儿
and whatever government rations we get.
上头给的补助粮也要平分着吃
Ratso,
黄鼠狼
youlll keep accounts,
给记上帐
Of Confucius keeps my books
孔者二 他给我管过账
O! Man Heaven looks after my fields
张天师他给我看菜园
fm god's own goddamn daddy
我本是老天爷的他干驳
from now until the day { die!
你看我体面不体面
Stop that!
胡说甚呢
No one's dying.
死不了的
Old Zhu's the godfather here,
老天爷是我们干驳
$0 he should be our headmaster.
你就是者天分派来的校长
Headmaster Zhu!
校长
Dad?
区
Instead of sleeping in the dorm,
我也和别人一块儿睡大屋子
what say f bunk with you?
要不我和你有睡吧
You've had your fill.
你都盛过了
Don't be so greedy,
你别多吃多占的
Dad, can you drop in
驳 你假装路过
and check on Haoyan?
看看她在家干甚
She trusts you,
郝艳听你的
$0 {thought
你劝劝她
you could talk her out of
我跟我哥也说了
not remarrying when I die.
让她将来守住 不要改嫁
Then {can rest in peace,
不然 我死了也不安生
Dont think dark thoughts.
咋不想点好的
What's so funny?
笑
Hell, look at the artist!
日能得很 画画了
You counting the days?
是画画吗
Every day counts,
多活一天是一天
if you make every day count.
多活一天赚一天
{t's worth remembering.
得记者
Assembly! Assembly in the schoolyard!
集合了 都出来集合了
See? it's not here.
你看呀
I foved your red silk jacket.
多漂亮的红绸只只
Howd you lose it?
咋能丢了呢
Qingin
琴琴
hung it on my bedpost.
我就放床头了
No
不用不用
fm warm enough in this,
我把两件毛衣都穿上了
Dad?
区
Let's search!
搜
Search the school!
不信搜不出
Whoever took it,
今天谁也不许回村
leave it in the schoolyard tonight.
东西半夜拿出来送院里
No questions asked!
我不追究
Dad?
区
You asleep?
你睡了
Haoyan went back to her mom's.
郝艳又回娘家了
She hasn't visited in ages.
她多少天没来看我
Ive been counting the days.
我都给她一天一天记着呢
What are you doing?
做其
! want to find out
帮你侦察一下
who the thief was,
哪个人来还东西了
Who's that?
谁
Oingin!
琴琴
Why are you out here in the middle of the night?
大半夜 你做其
! wanted to see who stole my jacket.
我想看看你们村 谁拿我的只只
My thoughts exactly.
那么巧
You scared?
琴琴 你怕不
So whyd you self your blood?
你为甚卖血
To buy this expensive shampoo
想买一瓶城里人用的洗发水
I saw on TV.
电视上有了呢
A girl from our village bought tt,
我们那儿有个女娃娃买了
and her hair was smooth as silk.
她的头发顺得像流水一样
! wanted to try it, too.
我也想 就卖了一回
You?
你呢
Everyone was selling blood,
谁都卖
My brother wouldn't let me,
我哥就是不让我卖
$0 f sold mine in another village.
我就跑到别的村卖去了
I heard he was a cheat.
人都说大哥黑
Took more blood than he paid for.
一袋血其实都抽一袋半了
They stole your jacket.
管谁偷你只只呢
Why not steal from them?
你也偷嘛
No, aff a person has is face,
人有脸 树要皮
To hell with face.
狗屁脸皮
Did you husband give you any?
你男人给你脸啊
When he heard you were sick,
一听说你有热病
he beat you.
就打了你一顿
Everyone knows.
全村人都知道
That's how little he cared,
你有病了
just enough to hit you,
还那么狠地打你
IF it were me,
换我
fd have infected him
有病我也不跟男人说
and never said a word.
非把热病传到他身上
Did you infect your wife?
你传给嫂子了
Truth is,
哥不怕你笑话
she hasnt touched me in over a year,
查出热病一年多
not since I was diagnosed.
她连手都不让我摸一下
Think about it...
你说
fm not even 30.
我还不到三十岁
Yeah, same here.
哥 都一样
My husband said
小海也说了
! was too filthy to be buried next to him.
他死了都不和我埋一块儿
What a shit!
坏外娃
IF it were me,
要是我
fd be proud to be buried by your side.
巴不得和你埋到一块儿呢
You must be cold.
冷吧
Oingin...
琴琴
! want to say something.
我想跟你说个避
Damn it...
他妈的
you and f belong together!
不如我们俩个好
Now's not the time.
现在不是挺好的吗
What better time is there?
不够好 还能更好
Halt...
立定
About, face!
向左转
Brush!
刷牙
Spit!
澈口
! just want to catch the thief.
我就是想抓住敢偷你只只的人
About, right!
向右转
Double time!
跑步走
Don't be scared, Mf help you fix him,
不要怕 我帮你拾援他
Is there no justice in this world?
狗日的无法无天了
There's no justice.
无法无天了
Stow down and tell me what happened.
四伦 你慢慢说
They stole my notebook and some money.
这几十年的事
put it under my pillow, and this morning
昨黑了睡觉
they were gone.
一觉醒来就没有了 没有了
! dont care about the money,
钱无所谓的
but that notebook... .
可那本本不能丢啊
I cantt lose it!
不能丢的呀
There's private stuff in there!
几十年来不能圈说的事情都记到上面了
Assembly!
集合了
ff search!
我去搜
Whoever steals, steals from me.
得罪人 我得罪
ff know who stole from my cousin's wife, too.
连我兄弟媳妇的只只一块儿找了
Search!
搜
Search party! Nobody move!
不动 找东西
Miss a woman's smell?
想闻女人味了
Shut it!
你胡球扯
Whose bed is this?
这谁的床
Confess and be punished!
坦白从严
Resist and we'lf be merciful!
抗拒从帘
Wait, other way around!
不对
Cook,
粮房
have you been stealing rice?
你拿灶房的米啦
No.
没有啊
You searched my bed?
你们搜我了
How could you?
不咏声就搜我床啦
!m up before dawn,
谁天不亮就起床
cooking and cleaning
饭给做好 吃完了还给洗了
Well,
我咱
fm sick, too!
我也有病了
Why should wait on you?
赁甚天天伺候你们了
fff were out working,
我要是没病出去给人家做饭
at least Id get paid!
不光给这么多粮食还得给几百块钱呢
Have I ever asked for a penny?
我问谁要过一分钱了
So [took a few grains of rice!
拿这么一点点粮食咋了
How could you be so cruel?
你们都昧良心啊
You're heartless!
还搜我
If your family needed rice that badly,
你家短这点粮食啊
you should have asked me.
短了我给你
! dont need your charity!
该我挣的我不要 要你的做甚了
Dad!
驳 找着了
Look!
区
You took the jacket?
吴宇真是你拿的
What about my diary?
还有我的本本呢
Have you seen it?
老疙次 我的日记本你见了吗
ft has sentimental value.
见了把它拿出来它不值钱的
{t's a red notebook.
是个红的
You'd think it was made of gold.
破本子当吃还是当喝
ft's not worth anything, { swear!
不值几个钱的
Qingin, about your jacket...
琴琴 那个
Qingin?
我 那个
Where's my notebook?
咋就找不着了呢
Time to eat!
四伦权吃饭了
Still missing your notebook?
还想你的本本呢
Silun!
四伦叔
Aren't you hungry?
你不吃饭吓
Hey, you found it.
哎 你找到本本了
Hows Silun?
四伦叔咋样了
He's not feeling well.
他不舒服
Not hungry.
不想吃饭
Silun was always impatient,
四伦爷人性子急
even more so after he lost his diary.
谁让那日记本里记了他一辈子的秘密
Everyone knows we all die sooner or later.
大家都说 死是早晚的事
What was his hurry?
你急什么呀
No one would sleep in the school again.
你一走 谁还敢再住那间屋子呀
And the next world was even emptier than this one.
那边世界上就比先前更空了
Dad!
区
After New Year,
过了十五
Im taking Little Jun to visit my mom.
小军他外婆还想让我们回娘家住两天
What's the point of having a wife
我们家的媳妇算是白要了
if you're never even here?
我也倒插门算了
Bro
ET 可
Stand back, everyone!
让开
Get your tof here!
卖豆腐了
You dropped your cigarette.
烟掉了
Hey, you dropped your cigarette.
你烟掉了
You dropped your cigarette!
烟掉啦
We're better off in the school.
还不如住学校呢
Go tell your dad.
你去跟老柱柱说说
He'll listen to you.
你有面子
She's right.
就是 你去好
Only if Qingin goes with me.
琴琴要去我就去
Go ahead, Qingin.
琴琴 去哇
{t's for the greater good
你也是为大家好
We're alone.
没有人
Did you miss me?
想我了
Didn't you miss me?
你没想我吗
! mostly thought about being sick.
我想着我的病呢
There's nothing to live for.
活着没意思
Nothing to live for?
没意思
ff give you something to live for!
那就活出个意思
! won't live out the year.
我猜我都活不过今年了
If you marry me,
你要原意嫁
fd take you,
我就敢娶你
And take you...
我就敢娶
Come on, Qingin!
琴琴 来呀
Deyi!
得意
Oingin!
琴琴
Get down!
你下来 得意
Stop it!
得意 你下来
Deyi!
得意
{t's dangerous!
危险
Oingin!
琴琴
You stupid bastard!
王八蛋
Deyi!
得意
Zhao Deyi!
赵得意
You stupid bastard!
你个王八蛋
fm god's own goddamn daddy... .
我本是老天爷他干驳
from now until the day I die...
你看我体面不体面
Open up!
开学了
Students reporting for class!
同学们来报到
When everyone moved back into the school,
大家又回学校了
their food attracted the usual scavengers,
到处混吃混喝的花脸猪也闻着味儿来了
Table scraps not good enough for you?
剩饭还不够你吃啊
This is people food,
这是新鲜粮食
ft's not for you.
我们还舍不得吃呢
Scram!
去了
Hey, what's my dad doing here?
看 我欧咋也来了
This is high-quality city flour.
这可是城里人吃的白面
Consider it my gift to you.
就算是我齐全
Hey...
我说
When the time comes,
都是自家人啊
Mf give you a discount.
给你们优惠
Dad, you think he bought that flour,
驳 你猜那面真是我哥自家的
or got it free from the government?
肯定是从政府那儿来的
Go to sleep.
睡觉
!'m just going to the toilet.
驳 我去赵茅房
Today Cook said
听粮房姐说
she thought she saw my husband,
她好像见到小海了
You think he came for me?
他是不是来看我的
Sure, fet him come.
来呀 他现在就来呀
Let him see your buttons missing.
来看看你的扣子 咋都扣成这样了
come on
来呀
Open the door.
把门开开吧
You got the key?
你有钥匙了
The lock's brand new.
大兄弟呀
Someone planned this,
人家早准备抓你们了
Dad?
区
Open the door!
先把门开开
Open the door first!
开开再说嘛
Dad!
区
Who's got the key?
把钥匙给我
Come on,
把门开开吧
Deyi doesn't deserve this.
得意比他哥齐全好多啦
Dad, smash the lock in!
驳 把锁磺开
Dad!
区
Come on, just smash the lock!
驳 把锁磺开啊
fi do it.
我来
Look,
快看
isnt that Qingin's husband?
那是不是琴琴的男人
Xiaohial...
小海
Cheat on me, will you?
我让你们搞
What the hell are you looking at?
看什么看
Get out there!
出去
Show them what a slut looks like!
臭寻子 我让你乱搞
See?
看看
Sfoppy slippers!
骚货
Xiaohai, she's sick,
小海 琴琴的热病已经不轻了
Let her go!
你就放过她吧
You mind your own business!
你先管好你儿子吧
Well, you had your fun.
笑话了
Glad could help entertain you.
让大家笑话了
You'll come to no good end!
你不得好死
fm a dead man anyway.
反正就是热病病死
Is this fair to Haoyan?
你对得起郝艳吗
She had a man before me.
郝艳嫁我前就有过男人了
{s that fair to me?
她对得起我吗
Then think of your son,
那你儿子呢
Oh...
哎呀
we thought you were inside.
报你没在屋啊
Come here, we need to talk.
来 叔 跟你说个事情 来
We locked them in, and gave
得意跟琴琴是我和黄鼠狼锁的
the key to Qingin's husband.
钥匙也是我给琴琴男人的
! wanted to give one to Deyts wife, too.
他还想给阁艳一把
But stopped him.
念你教过我 是我的老师
Out of respect for you.
不是说得意有甚好
We'd sure hate...
现在最怕
for her to find out.
郝艳知道
That's why we have a proposition.
所以有个事情想和叔商量一下
Well, that's alf f have to say.
我要说的就这些了
This schoo! needs some new blood,
他们俩年轻
$0 Im putting these two young men in charge.
往后学校里的事情就由他们俩张罗了
Rule One:
告示
ff you dont contribute
每个人兑粮入伙
your fair share of food,
缺厂短两者
may your whole family
全家都得热病
Two:
一
All government rations of
政府照顾的粮 油 药物等
food and medicine will be shared,
统一管理 分发个人
Cheaters and disobedients will see
不听指挥者
alf their ancestors and descendants die.
日他先人八辈后代十六辈
Three...
一
Deyi, { hear you scored the other day.
得意听说你占着便宜了
just take it day by day,
得意一天是一天
Three:
一
Adutterers and corrupters of public morals
偷鸡摸狗
will wear the sign of their shame
再被抓住者
and be paraded through the village streets!
游街示众
Stop right there!
给我停下
No one takes schoo! property!
东西谁也不许动
What happens when the kids come back?
谁保证娃娃不再回学校
What then?
谁敢保证
But we promised to divy things up!
叔
Besides,
你不要忘了
an understanding. ...
让我们来管事情的
Dad,
区
ft's not our stuff.
又不是我们家真子
Butt outithis is alf vour fault!
回去
Butt out! This is all vour fault!
不是你也没今天的事情
Have it your way.
不管还不行么
You'll take these things over my dead body!
只要我还守着学校
Zhao Lianzhu is fired!!
( 开除赵连柱 )
Starting today,
从今天起
you're fired from this school!
你再也不是娘娘庙小学的老师了
You're not fit to lead.
你早不配管学校了
Qiquan milked this village dry,
你大儿子抽光了村里人的血
and infected us with dirty blood!
还把染了病的脏血打给我们
Now he's profiting by selling coffins!
他还倒卖棺木
And your younger son's no better,
你家老二有媳妇
fooling around on his wife.
还和人家的媳妇胡搞
With his cousin's wife, no less!
搞的还是自己亲叔伯兄弟的妨妇
fm doing you a favor letting you stayhere!
还叫你住学校就算抬举你了
Let's go!
士 人
Still wont budge, huh?
还不让让
Here, dad,
区
Go home and work things out with your wife.
你回家看看吧
ft was obvious to her and everyone in the village.
我权和琴琴爱得像课本上的喜马拉雅山
Uncle and Qingin were in love.
全村人 全世界都看在眼里了
Qingin's husband finally kicked her out for good.
就这样 琴琴也被他丈夫小海赶回娘家了
Everyone moved out of the school,
转眼间 学校又散了
and grandpa was alone again.
又剩下他爷一个人了
Dad, Oiquan's back.
驳 我哥回来了
He wants to see you.
叫你去他家
We're moving into town soon.
准备准备我就搬走了
Then to the city,
先搬到县城
as soon as {can afford to.
以后钱多了再说
You can come with us if you want,
你跟我先搬到城里也能成
or stay here with Deyi,
留下来陪陪得意也能成
When he's gone,
等得意没了
you can come five with us,
再搬到我那儿
and Mf support you in your old age.
我给你养老送终也能成
After all, we're family.
说其你也是我亲驳
Is that...?
这是
Shush!
咕 别叶声
Wow, real leather!
这是真皮的
Holy shit...
他妈的
Can you imagine going
用这样的棺木到了那边儿
to the afterlife in this?
那得是甚日子
{t's worth dying for!
死也值了
Give us two coffins like this,
给我们两口
and all the trees in the village are yours!
村里的树我帮你砍
Old Zhu?
老柱柱
Ive been thinking it over.and { wanted to return this.
想来想去
Someone else might need it.
往后肯定还能用得上
The truth is,
不怕你笑话
when my wife and { got married,
想当初我跟娃他娘结婚的时候
! promised her a red silk jacket.
就许给她一件红岗只只
She's waited so fong, I just...
现在我的娃都要成家了
. wanted her to have one,
我…我真没出息
! didn't mean to steal,
真不是成心要偷
Grandpa made the long, long trip
爷爷来回走了几十里
to borrow Qingin's red silk jacket.
到琴琴娘家 又讨回了那红只只
Geda saw his wife wearing it just once before he died.
然后 老疙疤伯伯就真的没了
Dont take anything that isn't yours.
没拿别人东西吧
Xiaohai has a new fiancée.
不看了 小海快找着媳妇了
When the time comes,
如果到时候你还活着
give him a divorce, if you're still alive.
就回来离婚
Understand?
你听见没有
No one can see us.
没有人
Not that fd care if they did.
有人也不怕
You came back for your summer clothes?
回来拿夏天的衣党啊
How are you feeling?
病咋样
Dontt go.
不要走了
Haoyan's divorcing me.
郝艳要和我离婚了
Xiaohai's divorcing you.
小海也要和你离婚了
We're free.
都离了
Now we can be together.
我们俩一块儿过
No matter what happens while we live,
不光图活着是个样子
we can be buried together,
死了埋到一块儿
50 we won't be afone.
也是个伴儿
Why are you crying?
刁甚了
Let's five together.
我们就住一块儿
Who cares what they say?
给小海他们一家人看
Who cares what anyone says?
给郝站和全村人看
Let them try to stop us.
看别人能把我们俩咋样儿
Dontt go.
哪儿都不要去
Live with me.
住我家
And if my house is too fulf of memories,
要是怕看见郝艳用过的东西
we'll find someplace else.
我们再寻个啥地方
Oingin, come out you shameless whore!
商琴琴 你个能开进拖拉机的烂货
Shang Qingin!
商琴琴
Come out here right now!
听见没有
Shang Qingin! Come out here right now!
商琴琴你给我滚出来
She's my wife now.
二六
If there's a problem, talk to me.
有甚事 你找我
Your wife?
你媳妇
As long as she's married to Xiaohai,
没离婚 就是我小海的媳妇
she's still my daughter-in-law!
我们家的媳妇
You've got some nerve!
你咋这不要脸呢你
That's right. { seduced her,
就是不要脸 我勾引的琴琴
and now she's shacking up with me.
她要回娘家 我把她搜到这儿来了
So if you want to take it out on someone,
要打要骂冲我来
take it out on me,
琴琴就更是我的人了
You shameless...
不要脸的东西
Said enough?
骂够了没有
Go ahead, hit me.
来 炳 你往死里打
Beat me to death,
寻 你往死里打
Come on, do it...
来来来 往死里打
Who
谁
You greedy pig!
我叫你吃
Come back here!
我叫你跑
Come back!
你过来
Steal my rice, wilf you?
你还敢来偷我的米
Think you can out run me?
我看你往哪跑
Hey, let me off!
放我下来…
Look at her go!
项住顶住
Help!
救命啊
Hey bro...
ET 可
Ifyou need a hand, just ask!
要拿甚跟我们说一声
fm not that worthless yet!
你以为你哥我是洋火棍棍
Hey, bro...
ET 可
Sick as you are, can you still do it with Qingin?
你得了热病不耽拉你跟琴琴那事儿吧
Sure, twice a night.
每天晚上 两次
Hey,
ET 可
Wow.
浪啊
Wish I had the fever.
我咋就没有得热病呢
Want mine?
要不哥传给你
Qingin?
琴琴
! keep dreaming about my mom.
我最近老梦见我娘
She says she feels cold in her sleep
她说睡觉身子冷
and asks me to warm her feet.
叫我过去 给她业肢
When did she die?
你娘甚时候没的
About ten years ago.
十多年了
From now on, If be your mom.
那以后我就当你娘
When you calf her name,
别想你娘了
think of me.
想着我
Calf me mom,
叫我娘了
and Niove you any like your mother.
让我做甚我做其
and Ni ove you any way you want.
我就像亲娘一样疼你
Mom?
娘
! want your breast...
我要吃奶
You're awful!
坏死了
Next you'll want me to call you daddy,
还想让你当我欧呢
Here, come to daddy...
快让驳再把你心疼心疼
Blabber?
大嘴
Cook's gone.
粮房姐走了
After that pig ate her rice,
花脸猪把粮房姐放门口的米吃了
she got really mad.
粮房姐跟它生气了
Now she's gone,
走了
We're going to bury her with this bag of rice,
这是一袋米
$0 she doesn't leave empty-handed,
说别让她空手走
{t's out of batteries.
我的喇叭没电了
Kind of like me.
我也快没电了
No one expected,
谁也没想到
Cook to die so soon,
能吃能干的粮房娘先没了
Then Blabber died,
然后 大嘴哥哥也没了
and no one ever hear the sound of his megaphone again.
那边的世界就再也听不见大嘴哥哥的喇叭声响了
Let's get married.
咱们结婚吧
We've stiff got time...
趁活着
to make it official,
还能堂堂正正地过上几天
What do you say?
好不好
Daddy...
区
f want to marry Qingin.
我想要和琴琴结婚了
! need your help.
得你去找二闹
Talk Haiyan into divorcing me.
你说
to talk Haiyan into divorcing me.
琴琴要和小海离婚
No, f wortt do it,
我不去
My husband doesnit want me,
小海一家不要我了
and my family doesnt want me.
回娘家
Not even my own mother.
连我娘都嫌我
! know it's shameless,
我是不要脸
but I'm stiff here
可我没死
and life goes on.
我得活着
! want to be Deyi's wife.
跟得意结婚
Even if t's only for 6 months,
就算过半年
or a few weeks,
半个月
if we're married,
我们也是夫玫
we can be buried together,
死了就能堂堂正正地埋在一块儿
like family.
也是个家
Whys mommy crying?
驳 妈妈刁了
Xiaohai's out working!
小海家没人
To be honest,
实话跟你说
fve met someone.
我又找到妨妇了
She wants to get married this month,
原来讲好了
But how can f, when those two are shacking up
可他俩在我眼皮底下就敢住一块儿
and planning a wedding, too?
还想结婚了
We'll see who gives in first!
看谁获得过谁
Unele!
大伯
ff divorce Qingin on one condition.
要想让我成全他们 也能成
My fiancée wants a bigger house.
女方家嫌我房子小
Tell Deyi to leave me the house in his will.
不如等得意哥下世之后
That way, it's remains in the family.
肥水不流外人田嘛
When I get it in writing,
白纸黑字给我写下来
ff agree to the divorce.
今天写
Can your brother really get our marriage licenses,
我们俩要是不去
if we're not there in person?
大哥能把证领回来不
Of course.
大哥甚不能
No sweat.
领个证算其
Hey, it's almost winter.
立秋了
You shouldn't wash with cold water.
别用冷水控身子
fs that him?
ET 可
I bet it is?
没准儿是哥
Here,
来
drink this.
喝药
Daddy,
区
promise me something?
求你个事
Don't bury me in black,
能不能不穿寿衣
Buy me a dress,
我想穿裙子
A red dress.
红的
Ive always loved red.
我自小就喜欢红的
Come on, drink,
把药喝了吧
And something plain,
再买件素色的
$0 f have two outfits.
一红一素换着穿
Alf right.
成
And a pair of red high heels.
再给你买双新皮鞋
You can walk around in heaven
反正那边路平
in your high heels,
你就天天穿着高跟鞋
just like a city girl
像城里娃娃一样美
{tlt be great!
想去哪儿就去哪儿
You fie,
你骗我
You want me to die first.
你就想我先死
! didn't mean that.
我没那意思
Yes pou did,
你就那意思
$0 you can go back to your wife,
完了你还能找郝艳去
Want to know the truth?
话都是你说的
ve been sick longer than you!
我还比你早发病呢
You want to see me die first?
你想我现在就死给你看
Yes,
死啊
Okay!
死
How?
咋死
ff hang myself!
上吊
Alf right.
好啊
There's a rope in the closet.
麻强都在柜子里
if we die together,
我们今天一块儿死
ff know this wasnt all a waste.
我商琴琴也没白跟你睡在一张床上
Everyday counts,
多活一天是一天
! want to five,
我还要活着呢
But if you die,
娘死了
who'lf nurse me?
娃就没奶吃了
Mommy...
娘
Bro!
ET 可
Come on in,
进屋吧
You know what these cost me?
就为这两张破纸
A perfectly good coffin,
我又搭上一口上好的术木
You gave up everything for that slut,
你多有出息
even willed away the house.
把一辈子家产都给人
You'd be better off dead!
还不立马死掉
if not for dad,
要不是驳求我
! wouldnt have helped,
谁管你
Oingin...
琴琴
Mom...
娘
fm alf better.
我好了
My fever's gone.
不烧啦
! bought wedding candy.
我买喜精了
Come on.
起来
Get up.
起床
Deyi...
得意
! know ours is a second marriage,
我们虽然是二婚
but {still want everyone to know.
那我也想让全村人都知道
Get up.
起来
Mommy!
娘
Dey and { are married.
我和得意结婚了
See?
领证了
Here,
喜糖
have some wedding candy.
吃糖
Have some candy.
别客气
it's wedding candy.
喜糖
Dontt be shy.
拿着拿着
Congrats.
恭喜呵
See? Just like yours.
你看看我的证跟你领的一样不
{t's so red it looks fake, doesnt it?
我咋觉得红得跟假的似的
Ratso?
黄鼠狼
We're married,
我们结婚了
And we owe it alf to you,
这还得谢你呢
for locking us in the storeroom together.
过几天我们要是有娃了
See?
这是证
It's official,
看看
Ratso?
老黄
Come on!
来
Have some candy!
吃糖
Qingin, open your mouth.
琴琴 张开
Yummy, huh?
昏啊 甜
Unele and Qingin were married,
我皮和琴琴就这样结婚了
but their happiness,
他们不知道
but their happiness, it wouldn't last for long.
有一天喜马拉雅大山也会塌下来
That day, {too got married,
也是这一天
To a dead stranger, twice my age.
就在山的另一边
and they moved my bones far, far away.
他们要融我到很远的县城里
ve got mansions by the millions
好房舍我有八万间
and too many wives to count
老波子我有八万六
descendants in the billions
好儿孙我有十万三
fairy maids and goddesses to wait on me
王母娘娘来做饭
fm god's own goddamn daddy... .
我本是老天爷他干驳
from now until the day { die!
你说我体面不体面
Today...
今天
was Xin's wedding.
给小歼娶亲了
f didnt tell you
还没敢跟你说呢
in case you got upset.
怕你看到
Here.
拿着
You'd sacrifice your son for your own ambition?
你人五人六的 就折腾这亲
Her dad's the governor!
我们亲家
His word is law!
咳嗽一声谁都再想活
Now that we're family,
人家喜欢小窜
we're going into real estate.
我们还要在一起
We're going to turn this whole place
看就这儿 这儿
into a high-class cemetery,
马上就是一片高档陵园
& heaven on earth!
世外桃源
City folks will go nuts for it.
城里人能不抢
You think I care
我知道
that the villagers hate me?
娘娘庙人恨我
never set out to be evil
卖血我第一个去
but Mf be damned if 'm poor!
我不想恶 更不想穷
Few are born into luxury,
哪能人人都生在苏杭呢
but MI see that everyone is buried in it!
可是我
The pain's killing me!
活不成了
My leg!
我的腿
ft hurts!
腿好疼
Oh, god...
疼啊
Talk to me!
叫住我
ff someone has to go first,
怎么能活不成了呢
let it be me,
要走也得我先走啊
Your coffin isnt ready yet.
你哥还没把棺木给咱们呢
And! cantt live without you,
他要是不给
You know?
是不是啊
Can f ask you something?
我跟你说个事儿
Dont get mad.
你可别生气啊
Haoyan has someone else, doesnit she?
你告诉我
Tell me...
你说呀
Theyilf never be as happy as we are.
他俩再好
Havent always loved you like a mother?
我嫁给你做妨妇
When your wet your pants,
你裤子尿了
! washed them for you.
我给你洗
Whatever you wanted,
你要无赖
! gave you,
我让着你
Wasnt ! your mommy?
我真把自己当你娘了
Didn't f put my breast in your mouth
你说
and nurse you to sleep?
像哄娃娃一样
The minute we got our marriage license,
我发烧半个月了
my fever went away.
转眼就好了
You know why?
为甚呢
Because {love you.
我稀罕你
! fove being married to you.
我稀罕我们俩结婚了
Didn't I fove you enough?
我是不是对你还不够好啊
Why do you want to leave me?
你想早点离开我
Don't you want your Qingin?
你不想要琴琴了吗
Don't you want me?
你不要我了
! havent even had the chance to calf your dad father-in-law
还没来得及管老柱柱叫声驳呢
Tomorrow Mf bring him back here
明天我就把他接过来
and he can live with us,
接过来
ff cook for him,
我给他烧饭
and do the wash,
给他洗衣服
and knit for him
还给他织条毛裤
and for you,
也给你织
Alf right?
好不好
Dontt let me die, okay?
记得叫醒我
fm burning up...
着火了
Mommy...
娘
Ice, {need ice.
冰 冰 我要冰
Ice...
我要冰
Cant you hurry up?
你他妈的快点儿
Bring me ice...
娘 我要冰
Ice...
我要冰
fm burning up.
我要烧死了
Mommy...
娘
fm on fire...
着火了
fm thirsty,
渴
Mom
娘
Why don't you answer?
你咋不答应我呢
if you won't answer,
你应一声
ff just keep calling,
我就叫你一百声
Mom...
娘
Certificate of marriage!
结婚证
Zhao Deyi
赵得意
and Shang Qingin
商琴琴
Have some candy.
琴琴 糖
Zhao Deyi and Shang Qingin
赵得意 商琴琴
married of their own free wilf
自愿结婚
in full accordance
经审查
with the laws of the People's Republic of China.
符合中华人民共和国婚姻法
This license certifies their union,
关于结婚的规定
Zhao Deyi and Shang Qingin
赵得意 商琴琴
married of their own free wilf
自愿结婚
in full accordance with the laws of the People's Republic of China.
符合中华人民共和国婚姻法
This license certifies their union,
关于结婚的规定
Zhao Deyi and Shang Qingin
赵得意 商琴琴
with the laws of the People's Republic of China.
符合中华人民共和国婚姻法
This license certifies...
关于结婚的
their union.
规定
Certificate of marriage!
发给此证
Zhao Deyi and Shang Qingin
赵得意 商琴琴
Uncle gave me a beautiful aunt named Qingin.
我叔给我了了个漂亮妨妨叫商琴琴
I foved her too.
我也喜欢她
Because of a little red book,
因为有了红本本
they spent the rest of their days together.
他们就可以所守在一起 温天暖地的好
I'm here with Uncle, Auntie and the other villagers,
在你们那边 村人们在一起
just like you are with your loved ones,
和到了这边的村人们在一起
We work and five and love,and when the day is done,
我们也吃饭种地 过日子
we come together to telf our stories.
闲下来大家说笑听戏 还讲故事
My snows are pure white flour
俺这儿下雪下白面
And my rains are salt and cooking oif
下雨都下油共盐
My willows sprout coats of cotton woo!
俺这儿柳树顶上结棉鹤
Thick in winter, fine in summer
冬结棉来夏结单
Gold ingots grow from my elms
榆树项上结元宝
And silver dollars from my poplars
杨树项上都结银贺
Yuan Shikai tills my fields
豆世凯他给我种过地
Emperor Xuantong drives my cart
宣统他给我掌过大蒜
My houseboy is General Feng Yuxiang
冯玉祥他给我当伙计
My gardener is Taoist Master Zhang
张天师他给我看菜园
My cook is Goddess Wang Mu Niang
王母娘娘来做饭
My maids are fairy maidens
九天仙女给我当丫野
Confucius keeps my books
孔老二他给我管过帐
ve got thousands of mansions fair
好房舍我有八万间
ve got stables of the finest horses
我喂 着八万骤子八万马
And fields of good strong bulls
还喂八万老板肩(牛)
ve got mules to pull my millstones
还喂八万拉磨驴
And flour enough for all
磨了个白面大家餐
ve got more wives than I can handle
老波子我有八万六
And more kids that f can count
好儿孙我有十万三
fm god's own goddamn daddy
我本是老天爷他干驳
And dortt I look the part?
你看我体面不体面